[
  {
    "question": "When Samson killed 1000 Philistines at Lehi what weapon did he use?",
    "choices": [" Sword", " Spear", " Jawbone of an ass", " Bow and arrow"],
    "answer": " Jawbone of an ass",
    "categories": ["old testament", "judges"],
    "reference": "Judges 15:15"
  },
  {
    "question": "How old (years) was David when he was anointed King of Israel?",
    "choices": [" 25", " 30", " 35", " 40"],
    "answer": " 30",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "2 Samuel 5:4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aside from Peter and John, which disciple witnessed Jesus’ Transfiguration?",
    "choices": [" Andrew", " Philip", " James", " Matthew"],
    "answer": " James",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Matthew 17:1-2, Mark 9:2, Luke 9:28-29"
  },
  {
    "question": "In Damascus, whose sight was restored by Ananias?",
    "choices": [" Peter", " Paul", " Saul", " John"],
    "answer": " Saul",
    "categories": ["new testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Acts 9:17-18"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many rivers were formed from the river that went out of Eden?",
    "choices": [" 2", " 3", " 4", " 5"],
    "answer": " 4",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 2:10 (Pishon, Gihon, Hiddekel, and Euphrates)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the place where Jacob slept and dreamed of Jacob's Ladder?",
    "choices": [" Bethel", " Beersheba", " Hebron", " Jericho"],
    "answer": " Bethel",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 28:19"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who told Naaman to wash in the river Jordan 7 times in order to cure his leprosy?",
    "choices": [" Elijah", " Elisha", " Moses", " Joshua"],
    "answer": " Elisha",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "miracles"],
    "reference": "2 Kings 5:10"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who announced to Zachariah that his wife would bear a child to be named John the Baptist?",
    "choices": [
      " Angel Michael",
      " Angel Gabriel",
      " Angel Raphael",
      " Angel Uriel"
    ],
    "answer": " Angel Gabriel",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Luke 1:13"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who said, '…as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord'?",
    "choices": [" Moses", " Joshua", " Samuel", " David"],
    "answer": " Joshua",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Joshua 24:15"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the name 'Emmanuel' mean?",
    "choices": [" God with us", " God saves", " God provides", " God hears"],
    "answer": " God with us",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Matthew 2:23"
  },
  {
    "question": "God tested Abraham by telling him to offer his only son as a burnt offering. Who was that son?",
    "choices": [" Isaac", " Ishmael", " Jacob", " Esau"],
    "answer": " Isaac",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 22:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many pieces of silver was Judas paid to betray Jesus?",
    "choices": [" 20", " 25", " 30", " 40"],
    "answer": " 30",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 26:15"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who personally baptized more people, Jesus or John the Baptist?",
    "choices": [" Jesus", " John the Baptist", " Peter", " Paul"],
    "answer": " John the Baptist",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "John 4:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who witnessed Elijah being taken up to Heaven?",
    "choices": [" Elisha", " Samuel", " David", " Nathan"],
    "answer": " Elisha",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "miracles"],
    "reference": "2 Kings 2:11-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "Only 2 persons in the Bible are reported as being 'taken up to Heaven' (instead of dying). One is Elijah. Who is the other?",
    "choices": [" Moses", " Enoch", " Elisha", " Abraham"],
    "answer": " Enoch",
    "categories": ["old testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Genesis 5:24"
  },
  {
    "question": "Only 2 persons in the Bible are reported as being 'taken up to Heaven' (instead of dying). Who are they (in chronological order)?",
    "choices": [
      " Elijah and Enoch",
      " Enoch and Elijah",
      " Moses and Elijah",
      " Enoch and Moses"
    ],
    "answer": " Enoch and Elijah",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Genesis 5:24, 2 Kings 2:11-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who hid Joshua’s spies from Jericho’s king?",
    "choices": [" Rahab", " Deborah", " Jael", " Ruth"],
    "answer": " Rahab",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "Joshua 2:1-4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Moses died at age 120 and was buried in a valley of Moab. Who buried him?",
    "choices": [" Joshua", " The Lord", " Aaron", " The Israelites"],
    "answer": " The Lord",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "prophets"],
    "reference": "Deuteronomy 34:6"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many years were the Israelites in bondage in Egypt?",
    "choices": [" 200", " 300", " 400", " 430"],
    "answer": " 430",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus"],
    "reference": "Exodous 12:40-41"
  },
  {
    "question": "When they heard of the adversity that had befallen Job, how many of his friends came to comfort him?",
    "choices": [" 2", " 3", " 4", " 5"],
    "answer": " 3",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Job 2:11"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the only woman mentioned in Paul’s letter to Philemon?",
    "choices": [" Priscilla", " Lydia", " Apphia", " Chloe"],
    "answer": " Apphia",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Philemon 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What part of the day did Christ embark on the boat from which He calmed the waters?",
    "choices": [" Morning", " Afternoon", " Evening", " Midnight"],
    "answer": " Evening",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Mark 4:35"
  },
  {
    "question": "After his epiphany, how many years did Paul spend in Arabia before beginning his ministry?",
    "choices": [" 1", " 2", " 3", " 4"],
    "answer": " 3",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Galatians 1:18"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many troops did Sennacherib lose at the siege of Jerusalem?",
    "choices": [" 185,000", " 150,000", " 200,000", " 175,000"],
    "answer": " 185,000",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "2 Kings 19:35"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the father of John the Baptist?",
    "choices": [" Zechariah", " Joseph", " Simeon", " Nicodemus"],
    "answer": " Zechariah",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Luke 3:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many demons came out of Mary called Magdalene?",
    "choices": [" 5", " 6", " 7", " 8"],
    "answer": " 7",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Luke 8:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the multitude came out to be baptized, how did John the Baptist characterize them?",
    "choices": [
      " Children of Abraham",
      " Flock of sheep",
      " Brood of vipers",
      " Lost souls"
    ],
    "answer": " Brood of vipers",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Luke 3:7"
  },
  {
    "question": "From what tribe of Israel did the Apostle Paul come?",
    "choices": [" Judah", " Levi", " Benjamin", " Reuben"],
    "answer": " Benjamin",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Philippians 3:5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who directed Paul to preach to the Gentiles?",
    "choices": [" Peter", " John", " James", " Jesus"],
    "answer": " Jesus",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Acts 26:17"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the king of Israel when David slew Goliath?",
    "choices": [" Saul", " David", " Solomon", " Rehoboam"],
    "answer": " Saul",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 17"
  },
  {
    "question": "To whom did God describe Job as a perfect and upright man?",
    "choices": [" Job's wife", " Satan", " Job's friends", " Job's children"],
    "answer": " Satan",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Job 1:8"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who said, “Silver and Gold have I none, but such as I have I give thee?”",
    "choices": [" Peter", " Paul", " John", " James"],
    "answer": " Peter",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Acts 3:6"
  },
  {
    "question": "James, the brother of John, was the first Apostle martyred. How was he killed?",
    "choices": [" Crucified", " Stoned", " With a sword", " Beheaded"],
    "answer": " With a sword",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Acts 12:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "How old (in years) was Abraham when his son Isaac was born?",
    "choices": [" 90", " 95", " 100", " 105"],
    "answer": " 100",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 21:5"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the title placed on Jesus’ cross?",
    "choices": [" King of the Jews", " Son of God", " Messiah", " Savior"],
    "answer": " King of the Jews",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Luke 24:38, John 19:19"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who took his rod and stretched out his hand upon the waters of Egypt to turn them into blood?",
    "choices": [" Moses", " Aaron", " Joshua", " Elijah"],
    "answer": " Aaron",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "prophets", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7:19-20"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where (city) were the disciples first called Christians?",
    "choices": [" Jerusalem", " Antioch", " Rome", " Corinth"],
    "answer": " Antioch",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Acts 11:26"
  },
  {
    "question": "When Jesus struggled with his cross, who was forced to bear it for him?",
    "choices": [
      " Simon from Cyrene",
      " Joseph of Arimathea",
      " Peter",
      " John"
    ],
    "answer": " Simon from Cyrene",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Mark 15:21; Matthew 27:32"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the Book of Revelations, what needs to be done to receive the crown of life?",
    "choices": [
      " Faithful until death",
      " Giving to the poor",
      " Preaching the gospel",
      " Praying constantly"
    ],
    "answer": " Faithful until death",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Revelations 2:10"
  },
  {
    "question": "What body of water, other than the Red Sea, was parted in the Bible?",
    "choices": [
      " Nile River",
      " Euphrates River",
      " Jordan River",
      " Tigris River"
    ],
    "answer": " Jordan River",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "By Joshua (Joshua 3:7-4:18), and by Elijah and Elisha (2 Kings 2:2-8 and 13-14)"
  },
  {
    "question": "How tall was Goliath?",
    "choices": [" 4 cubits", " 5 cubits", " 6 cubits and a span", " 7 cubits"],
    "answer": " 6 cubits and a span",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 17:4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What did Paul say was the fulfillment of the Law?",
    "choices": [" Faith", " Hope", " Love", " Charity"],
    "answer": " Love",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Romans 13:10"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the shortest chapter in the Bible?",
    "choices": [" Psalm 116", " Psalm 117", " Psalm 118", " Psalm 119"],
    "answer": " Psalm 117",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Psalm 117 (2 verses)"
  },
  {
    "question": "There are only two perfect cubes described in Scripture. What is the one described in Revelation?",
    "choices": [
      " New Jerusalem",
      " Solomon's Temple",
      " Ark of the Covenant",
      " Tower of Babel"
    ],
    "answer": " New Jerusalem",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Revelation 21:16"
  },
  {
    "question": "God parted the Red Sea so Moses and the Israelites could cross. What body of water did He part so Joshua and the Israelites could cross?",
    "choices": [
      " Nile River",
      " Euphrates River",
      " Jordan River",
      " Tigris River"
    ],
    "answer": " Jordan River",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Joshua 3:15-17"
  },
  {
    "question": "At Christ’s crucifixion what time of day did darkness come over the whole land?",
    "choices": [" Morning", " Noon", " Afternoon", " Evening"],
    "answer": " Noon",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 27:45"
  },
  {
    "question": "At Christ’s crucifixion darkness come over the whole land. How long did it last?",
    "choices": [" 1 hour", " 2 hours", " 3 hours", " 4 hours"],
    "answer": " 3 hours",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 27:45"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many persons were sealed as 'servants of our God on their forehead'?",
    "choices": [" 12,000", " 72,000", " 120,000", " 144,000"],
    "answer": " 144,000",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Revelations 7:4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the City of God?",
    "choices": [" Jerusalem", " New Jerusalem", " Bethlehem", " Zion"],
    "answer": " New Jerusalem",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Revelations 3:12"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the father of David?",
    "choices": [" Jesse", " Saul", " Solomon", " Jonathan"],
    "answer": " Jesse",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "Ruth 4:22"
  },
  {
    "question": "To which king did Isaac hide his spousal relationship with Rebecca by claiming she was his sister?",
    "choices": [" Pharaoh", " Abimelech", " Nebuchadnezzar", " Ahasuerus"],
    "answer": " Abimelech",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 26:1-9"
  },
  {
    "question": "3 named women found Christ’s tomb open and empty: Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother of James, and _____?",
    "choices": [" Joanna", " Martha", " Salome", " Susanna"],
    "answer": " Joanna",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Luke 24:10"
  },
  {
    "question": "3 named women found Christ’s tomb open and empty: Joanna, Mary the mother of James, and _____?",
    "choices": [" Martha", " Mary Magdalene", " Salome", " Susanna"],
    "answer": " Mary Magdalene",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Luke 24:10"
  },
  {
    "question": "3 named women found Christ’s tomb open and empty: Mary Magdalene, Joanna, and _____?",
    "choices": [" Mary", " Martha", " Salome", " Susanna"],
    "answer": " Mary",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Luke 24:10 (the mother of James)"
  },
  {
    "question": "To which tribe of Israel did Moses belong?",
    "choices": [" Judah", " Levi", " Benjamin", " Reuben"],
    "answer": " Levi",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "prophets"],
    "reference": "Exodus 2:1"
  },
  {
    "question": "To what land did Moses flee after killing the Egyptian soldier?",
    "choices": [" Canaan", " Midian", " Egypt", " Edom"],
    "answer": " Midian",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "exodus"],
    "reference": "Exodus 2:15"
  },
  {
    "question": "Christ’s first miracle was turning water into wine. Where did this occur?",
    "choices": [" Jerusalem", " Bethlehem", " Cana of Galilee", " Nazareth"],
    "answer": " Cana of Galilee",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "John 2:6-9, 11"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sarah was Abraham’s first wife. Who was his second?",
    "choices": [" Hagar", " Keturah", " Rebekah", " Leah"],
    "answer": " Keturah",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 25:1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What relic did Moses remove from Egypt at the time of the Exodus?",
    "choices": [
      " Ark of the Covenant",
      " Staff of Aaron",
      " Bones of Joseph",
      " Tablets of the Law"
    ],
    "answer": " Bones of Joseph",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "exodus"],
    "reference": "Exodus 13:19"
  },
  {
    "question": "How old was Abraham when he was circumcised?",
    "choices": [" 90", " 95", " 99", " 100"],
    "answer": " 99",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 17"
  },
  {
    "question": "After Christ’s triumphal entrance into Jerusalem and after visiting the temple, where did he spend the night?",
    "choices": [" Bethany", " Bethlehem", " Nazareth", " Capernaum"],
    "answer": " Bethany",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Mark 11:11"
  },
  {
    "question": "The first two disciples selected by Jesus were brothers. Name them in alphabetical order (____ and ____).",
    "choices": [
      " Andrew and Simon",
      " James and John",
      " Peter and Andrew",
      " Philip and Nathanael"
    ],
    "answer": " Andrew and Simon",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Mark 1:16"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the tribes of Israel was prohibited from owning land in Canaan?",
    "choices": [" Judah", " Ephraim", " Levites", " Manasseh"],
    "answer": " Levites",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Deuteronomy 18:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What city is called the City of David?",
    "choices": [" Jerusalem", " Bethlehem", " Nazareth", " Hebron"],
    "answer": " Bethlehem",
    "categories": ["old testament", "new testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "Luke 2:4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who ate honey out of a lion’s carcass?",
    "choices": [" David", " Samson", " Elijah", " Jonathan"],
    "answer": " Samson",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "Judges 14:5-9"
  },
  {
    "question": "What famous city did Nebuchadnezzar rule?",
    "choices": [" Nineveh", " Babylon", " Jerusalem", " Tyre"],
    "answer": " Babylon",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "??"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was Israel’s first high priest?",
    "choices": [" Moses", " Joshua", " Aaron", " Eli"],
    "answer": " Aaron",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "exodus"],
    "reference": "Exodus 28"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the only woman whose age is mentioned in the Bible?",
    "choices": [" Eve", " Sarah", " Ruth", " Esther"],
    "answer": " Sarah",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 23:1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which books in the Bible are named after women? (____ and ____, in order of appearance in the Bible)",
    "choices": [
      " Esther and Ruth",
      " Ruth and Esther",
      " Judith and Esther",
      " Ruth and Judith"
    ],
    "answer": " Ruth and Esther",
    "reference": "Ruth and Esther",
    "categories": ["old testament"]
  },
  {
    "question": "How many Jews were exiled to Babylon by Nebuchadnezzar?",
    "choices": [" 3000", " 4000", " 4600", " 5000"],
    "answer": " 4600",
    "reference": "Jeremiah 52:30",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"]
  },
  {
    "question": "When Moses was preparing the Israelites for their coming confrontation with the 7 nations of Canaan, how large an army (number) did he raise?",
    "choices": [" 500000", " 603550", " 700000", " 800000"],
    "answer": " 603550",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "Numbers 1:46"
  },
  {
    "question": "When God finally let the Israelites enter the promised land of Canaan, how many nations had to be destroyed?",
    "choices": [" 5", " 6", " 7", " 8"],
    "answer": " 7",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus"],
    "reference": "Acts 13:19"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who leapt in his mother’s womb when Mary visited?",
    "choices": [" Jesus", " John the Baptist", " Peter", " James"],
    "answer": " John the Baptist",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Luke 1:41"
  },
  {
    "question": "After the 5000 ate their fill of the 5 loaves and 2 fishes, how much food was left over?",
    "choices": [" 10 baskets", " 11 baskets", " 12 baskets", " 13 baskets"],
    "answer": " 12 baskets",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Matthew 14:20"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the 7th day, how many times did Joshua’s army march around Jericho before the walls fell?",
    "choices": [" 5", " 6", " 7", " 8"],
    "answer": " 7",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Joshua 6:5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who did God describe as 'a blameless and upright man'?",
    "choices": [" Abraham", " Moses", " Job", " David"],
    "answer": " Job",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Job 1:8"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aside from the Serpent, what other animal in the Old Testament spoke to humans?",
    "choices": [" Lion", " Donkey", " Horse", " Eagle"],
    "answer": " Donkey",
    "categories": ["old testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Numbers 22:28-30"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whose flock was Moses tending when he encountered the burning bush?",
    "choices": [" Jethro", " Laban", " Reuel", " Aaron"],
    "answer": " Jethro",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 3:1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who said, 'Silver and gold have I none; but such as I have I give thee'?",
    "choices": [" Peter", " Paul", " John", " James"],
    "answer": " Peter",
    "categories": ["new testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Acts 3:6"
  },
  {
    "question": "How long was Jonah in the belly of the great fish?",
    "choices": [
      " 1 day and 1 night",
      " 2 days and 2 nights",
      " 3 days and 3 nights",
      " 4 days and 4 nights"
    ],
    "answer": " 3 days and 3 nights",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets"],
    "reference": "Jonah 1:17"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many days did Joshua’s troops march around Jerico before the walls fell?",
    "choices": [" 5", " 6", " 7", " 8"],
    "answer": " 7",
    "categories": ["old testament", "miracles", "exodus"],
    "reference": "Joshua 6:3-5: Hebrews 11:3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is King David buried?",
    "choices": [" Jerusalem", " City of David", " Hebron", " Bethlehem"],
    "answer": " City of David",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "1 Kings 2:10 (aka Old Jerusalem)"
  },
  {
    "question": "At the transfiguration who appeared and talked to Christ? (____ and ____, in their respective order in the Bible)",
    "choices": [
      " Elijah and Moses",
      " Moses and Elijah",
      " Abraham and Moses",
      " Moses and Abraham"
    ],
    "answer": " Moses and Elijah",
    "reference": "Matthew 17:3; Mark 9:4; Luke 9:30",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "prophets"]
  },
  {
    "question": "How many Beatitudes are there?",
    "choices": [" 7", " 8", " 9", " 10"],
    "answer": " 8",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 5:3-10"
  },
  {
    "question": "How old (in years) was Noah when the flood was upon the earth?",
    "choices": [" 500", " 600", " 700", " 800"],
    "answer": " 600",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 4:6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of Joseph’s (coat of many colors) 11 brothers said to his brothers not to kill Joseph but to cast him in a pit instead?",
    "choices": [" Reuben", " Simeon", " Judah", " Levi"],
    "answer": " Reuben",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 37:21-22"
  },
  {
    "question": "Paul said he would visit the Romans on this journey to which country?",
    "choices": [" Greece", " Spain", " Egypt", " Turkey"],
    "answer": " Spain",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Romans 15:24"
  },
  {
    "question": "How old (years) was Adam when he died?",
    "choices": [" 900", " 930", " 950", " 970"],
    "answer": " 930",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 5:3"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many times was Peter told to forgive his brother who had sinned against him?",
    "choices": [
      " Seven times",
      " Seventy times seven times",
      " Forty-nine times",
      " Seventy times"
    ],
    "answer": " Seventy times seven times",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 18:22"
  },
  {
    "question": "After his epiphany on the road to Damascus, how many days was Saul without sight?",
    "choices": [" 1", " 2", " 3", " 4"],
    "answer": " 3",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Acts 9:9"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is Moses buried?",
    "choices": [
      " Mount Sinai",
      " Valley of Moab",
      " Mount Nebo",
      " Wilderness of Zin"
    ],
    "answer": " Valley of Moab",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus"],
    "reference": "Deuteronomy 34:6 (in the valley)"
  },
  {
    "question": "About how long was Christ on the cross before he said “My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me?”",
    "choices": [" 6 hours", " 7 hours", " 8 hours", " 9 hours"],
    "answer": " 9 hours",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 27:46"
  },
  {
    "question": "How old was Moses when he died?",
    "choices": [" 110", " 115", " 120", " 125"],
    "answer": " 120",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus"],
    "reference": "Deuteronomy 34:7"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Paul in Romans, how many righteous people are there? (number)",
    "choices": [" 0", " 1", " 2", " 3"],
    "answer": " 0",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Romans 3:10"
  },
  {
    "question": "Adam and Eve had 3 sons. Cain was the firstborn followed by Abel. Who was the third son?",
    "choices": [" Seth", " Enosh", " Lamech", " Methuselah"],
    "answer": " Seth",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 4:25"
  },
  {
    "question": "To whom did Jesus say, 'Man shall not live by bread alone.'?",
    "choices": [" Peter", " Satan", " John", " Judas"],
    "answer": " Satan",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 4:4"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many loaves and fishes did Jesus use to feed the multitude of 5000? (__ loaves and ___ fishes)",
    "choices": [
      " 4 loaves and 1 fish",
      " 5 loaves and 2 fishes",
      " 6 loaves and 3 fishes",
      " 7 loaves and 4 fishes"
    ],
    "answer": " 5 loaves and 2 fishes",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Mark 6:41; Matthew 14:17; John 6:9; Luke 9:13"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the city founded by Cain?",
    "choices": [" Enoch", " Lamech", " Methuselah", " Jubal"],
    "answer": " Enoch",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 4:17"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many days had Lazarus been dead before being risen by Jesus?",
    "choices": [" 2", " 3", " 4", " 5"],
    "answer": " 4",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "John 11:39"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many devils were cast out of Mary Magdalene?",
    "choices": [" 5", " 6", " 7", " 8"],
    "answer": " 7",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Luke 8:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What did John the Baptist eat while preaching in the Judean wilderness?",
    "choices": [
      " Bread and water",
      " Locusts and wild honey",
      " Fish and bread",
      " Dates and figs"
    ],
    "answer": " Locusts and wild honey",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 3:4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the mountain from which Moses viewed Canaan and on which he died.",
    "choices": [" Sinai", " Carmel", " Nebo", " Zion"],
    "answer": " Nebo",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Deuteronomy 32:49-50"
  },
  {
    "question": "For refusing to worship a false god, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego were cast into a fiery furnace by King Nebuchadnezzar. How many times hotter than normal did the king order the furnace fire to be?",
    "choices": [" 3", " 5", " 7", " 10"],
    "answer": " 7",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Daniel 3:19"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the only Gentile in the Bible to be identified as the Lord’s anointed?",
    "choices": [" Nebuchadnezzar", " Cyrus", " Darius", " Xerxes"],
    "answer": " Cyrus",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "Isaiah 45:1 [King of Persia 580 BC – 529 BC]"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the shortest verse in the Bible?",
    "choices": [
      " 'Jesus wept'",
      " 'God is love'",
      " 'Rejoice always'",
      " 'Pray without ceasing'"
    ],
    "answer": " 'Jesus wept'",
    "reference": "John 11:35",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"]
  },
  {
    "question": "In Genesis two men are identified as having walked with God. Who are they? (____ and ____, alphabetical order)",
    "choices": [
      " Enoch and Methuselah",
      " Enoch and Noah",
      " Methuselah and Noah",
      " Noah and Seth"
    ],
    "answer": " Enoch and Noah",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 5:24 and Genesis 6:9"
  },
  {
    "question": "Jacob and Esau were twin brothers. Name their father and mother respectively. (____ and _____)",
    "choices": [
      " Isaac and Rebecca",
      " Abraham and Sarah",
      " Isaac and Rachel",
      " Abraham and Hagar"
    ],
    "answer": " Isaac and Rebecca",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 25:19"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who negotiated with God to not destroy Sodom if but 10 righteous people could be found there?",
    "choices": [" Lot", " Abraham", " Isaac", " Jacob"],
    "answer": " Abraham",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 18:23-32"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the 1st plague God inflicted on Egypt?",
    "choices": [
      " Frogs",
      " Locusts",
      " Darkness",
      " River waters turned to blood"
    ],
    "answer": " River waters turned to blood",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the 2nd plague God inflicted on Egypt?",
    "choices": [
      " Frogs",
      " Locusts",
      " Darkness",
      " River waters turned to blood"
    ],
    "answer": " Frogs",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the 3rd plague God inflicted on Egypt?",
    "choices": [" Flies", " Frogs", " Lice", " Locusts"],
    "answer": " Lice",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the 4th plague God inflicted on Egypt?",
    "choices": [" Frogs", " Hail", " Flies", " Boils"],
    "answer": " Flies",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the 5th plague God inflicted on Egypt?",
    "choices": [" Boils", " Death of animals", " Locusts", " Darkness"],
    "answer": " Death of animals",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the 6th plague God inflicted on Egypt?",
    "choices": [" Boils", " Frogs", " Hail", " Lice"],
    "answer": " Boils",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the 7th plague God inflicted on Egypt?",
    "choices": [" Hail", " Darkness", " Locusts", " Death of first-born son"],
    "answer": " Hail",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the 8th plague God inflicted on Egypt?",
    "choices": [" Frogs", " Locusts", " Lice", " Flies"],
    "answer": " Locusts",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the 9th plague God inflicted on Egypt?",
    "choices": [" Darkness", " Hail", " Boils", " Frogs"],
    "answer": " Darkness",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the 10th plague God inflicted on Egypt?",
    "choices": [" Death of first-born son", " Frogs", " Lice", " Flies"],
    "answer": " Death of first-born son",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many plagues did God inflict on Egypt?",
    "choices": [" 7", " 8", " 9", " 10"],
    "answer": " 10",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Exodus 7-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many books are in the New Testament?",
    "choices": [" 24", " 25", " 26", " 27"],
    "answer": " 27",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "-nil-"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city was Jesus entering when Zacchaeus climbed a sycamore tree to see him?",
    "choices": [" Jerusalem", " Jericho", " Bethlehem", " Nazareth"],
    "answer": " Jericho",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Luke 19:1-4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the longest chapter in the Bible?",
    "choices": [" Psalm 117", " Psalm 118", " Psalm 119", " Psalm 120"],
    "answer": " Psalm 119",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Psalm 119 (176 verses)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where did Cain go when he left Eden?",
    "choices": [" Nod", " Canaan", " Egypt", " Midian"],
    "answer": " Nod",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 4:16"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who replaced Judas as the twelfth apostle?",
    "choices": [" Paul", " Matthias", " Barnabas", " Silas"],
    "answer": " Matthias",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Acts 1:15-26"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the most common name in the Bible?",
    "choices": [" John", " Mary", " Zechariah", " Joseph"],
    "answer": " Zechariah",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "-nil-"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of what were the 12 gates of New Jerusalem made?",
    "choices": [" Gold", " Silver", " Pearls", " Bronze"],
    "answer": " Pearls",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Revelations 21:21"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name Jezebel’s husband.",
    "choices": [" Ahab", " Jehu", " Jehoshaphat", " Omri"],
    "answer": " Ahab",
    "reference": "1 Kings 16:31",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"]
  },
  {
    "question": "Which timber was used to construct the Ark of Noah?",
    "choices": [" Cedar", " Oak", " Gopher", " Pine"],
    "answer": " Gopher",
    "reference": "Genesis 6:14",
    "categories": ["old testament"]
  },
  {
    "question": "Name Moses’ brother.",
    "choices": [" Aaron", " Joshua", " Caleb", " Eliezer"],
    "answer": " Aaron",
    "reference": "Exodus 7:1",
    "categories": ["old testament"]
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the age of Moses (years) at the time of his demise?",
    "choices": [" 110", " 115", " 120", " 125"],
    "answer": " 120",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Deuteronomy 34:7"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the Bible, God is said to have physically written thrice – each time on a different surface. On what did his writing appear at the third instance?",
    "choices": [" Stone tablets", " Sand", " Wall", " Parchment"],
    "answer": " Wall",
    "categories": ["old testament", "miracles", "prophets"],
    "reference": "Dan 5:5-12"
  },
  {
    "question": "Balaam was spoken to by which animal?",
    "choices": [" Donkey", " Lion", " Eagle", " Serpent"],
    "answer": " Donkey",
    "categories": ["old testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Numbers 22:22-35"
  },
  {
    "question": "What prophet issued ominous warning against people who took advantage of widows and the fatherless?",
    "choices": [" Isaiah", " Jeremiah", " Malachi", " Ezekiel"],
    "answer": " Malachi",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets"],
    "reference": "Malachi 3:5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who did Mordecai refuse to bow down to?",
    "choices": [" Ahasuerus", " Haman", " Zeresh", " Vashti"],
    "answer": " Haman",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Esther"
  },
  {
    "question": "How old in years was Moses when he died?",
    "choices": [" 110", " 115", " 120", " 125"],
    "answer": " 120",
    "categories": ["old testament", "exodus"],
    "reference": "Deuteronomy 34:7"
  },
  {
    "question": "How long was Daniel in the den of the lions?",
    "choices": [" 1 night", " 2 nights", " 3 nights", " 4 nights"],
    "answer": " 1 night",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Daniel 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "What animal is mentioned most frequently in both the New and Old Testaments?",
    "choices": [" Goat", " Lamb", " Sheep", " Ox"],
    "answer": " Sheep",
    "categories": ["old testament", "new testament"],
    "reference": "-nil-"
  },
  {
    "question": "How much time did Jonah spend in the belly of the whale?",
    "choices": [
      " 1 day and 1 night",
      " 2 days and 2 nights",
      " 3 days and 3 nights",
      " 4 days and 4 nights"
    ],
    "answer": " 3 days and 3 nights",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets"],
    "reference": "Jonah 1:17"
  },
  {
    "question": "What biblical Babylonian king cast Daniel into the lion’s den for praying to God in defiance of a royal decree?",
    "choices": [" Nebuchadnezzar", " Belshazzar", " Darius the Mede", " Cyrus"],
    "answer": " Darius the Mede",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "kings", "judges", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Daniel 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the Bible, what weapons was the Philistine giant, Goliath carrying when he was slain by David? (_____ and _____)",
    "choices": [
      " Sword and shield",
      " Sword and spear",
      " Shield and spear",
      " Bow and arrow"
    ],
    "answer": " Sword and spear",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 17:45"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the longest name in the Bible? (no need to type in the dashes)",
    "choices": [
      " Mephibosheth",
      " Nebuchadnezzar",
      " Maher-shalal-bash-baz",
      " Artaxerxes"
    ],
    "answer": " Maher-shalal-bash-baz",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Isaiah 8:1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who came to Zechariah to tell him that his wife would soon be having a baby?",
    "choices": [
      " Angel Michael",
      " Angel Gabriel",
      " Angel Raphael",
      " Angel Uriel"
    ],
    "answer": " Angel Gabriel",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Luke 1:19"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the Bible, how many pearly gates are there?",
    "choices": [" 10", " 11", " 12", " 13"],
    "answer": " 12",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Revelation 21:12-21"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the Bible, which of the 4 horsemen of the Apocalypse rides a red horse?",
    "choices": [" Conquest", " War", " Famine", " Death"],
    "answer": " War",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Revelation 6:1-8"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the color of the horse which the 'War' horseman of the Apocalypse rides?",
    "choices": [" White", " Red", " Black", " Pale"],
    "answer": " Red",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Revelation 6:1-8"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the Bible, which of the 4 horsemen of the Apocalypse rides a pale/ashen horse?",
    "choices": [" Conquest", " War", " Famine", " Death"],
    "answer": " Death",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Revelation 6:1-8"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who tells the disciples that Jesus had risen from the dead?",
    "choices": [" Mary Magdalene", " Peter", " John", " Thomas"],
    "answer": " Mary Magdalene",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 28:1-10, John 20:1-10"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many times did Peter deny Jesus?",
    "choices": [" 2", " 3", " 4", " 5"],
    "answer": " 3",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 26:33-35, Mark 14:29-31, Luke 22:33-34, John 13:36-38"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who fled from Iconium when they heard of a plot to stone them? (___ and ____, alphabetical order)",
    "choices": [
      " Barnabas and Paul",
      " Peter and John",
      " Paul and Silas",
      " Thomas and Matthew"
    ],
    "answer": " Barnabas and Paul",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Acts 14:5-6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the first king of Israel?",
    "choices": [" Saul", " David", " Solomon", " Samuel"],
    "answer": " Saul",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 10:1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of tree did Zacchaeus climb to see Jesus enter Jericho?",
    "choices": [" Olive", " Fig", " Sycamore", " Cedar"],
    "answer": " Sycamore",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Luke 19:1-4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was able to decipher Nebuchadnezzar’s dreams?",
    "choices": [" Joseph", " Daniel", " Ezekiel", " Isaiah"],
    "answer": " Daniel",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "kings", "judges", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Daniel 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was Joseph’s master in Egypt as stated in Genesis 37:36?",
    "choices": [" Pharaoh", " Potiphar", " Laban", " Abimelech"],
    "answer": " Potiphar",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 37:36"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the disciple who was a tax collector.",
    "choices": [" Peter", " John", " Matthew", " Thomas"],
    "answer": " Matthew",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 10:3, Mark 2:14, Luke 5:27"
  },
  {
    "question": "What king of Judah was stricken with leprosy?",
    "choices": [" Uzziah", " Hezekiah", " Josiah", " Manasseh"],
    "answer": " Uzziah",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "2 Kings 15:5 (also known as Azariah)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What king of Israel had a reputation as a fast and furious chariot driver?",
    "choices": [" Ahab", " Jehu", " Saul", " David"],
    "answer": " Jehu",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "2 Kings 9:20"
  },
  {
    "question": "What occurred when Jonathan and his armor-bearer attacked the Philistines?",
    "choices": [" Thunderstorm", " Fire", " Earthquake", " Flood"],
    "answer": " Earthquake",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges", "miracles"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 14:11-15"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who built the first altar?",
    "choices": [" Abraham", " Noah", " Moses", " Jacob"],
    "answer": " Noah",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 8:20"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many shekels did Abraham pay to buy the field of Machpelah?",
    "choices": [" 100", " 200", " 300", " 400"],
    "answer": " 400",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 23:16"
  },
  {
    "question": "After he fled for his life, which tree did Elijah sleep under?",
    "choices": [" Oak", " Cedar", " Juniper", " Fig"],
    "answer": " Juniper",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "1 Kings 19:5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Judas betrayed Jesus for exactly how many coins of silver?",
    "choices": [" 20", " 25", " 30", " 35"],
    "answer": " 30",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Matthew 26:15"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name David’s father.",
    "choices": [" Jesse", " Saul", " Solomon", " Jonathan"],
    "answer": " Jesse",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 17:12"
  },
  {
    "question": "God is not mentioned in only 1 book of the Bible. Which one?",
    "choices": [" Ruth", " Esther", " Song of Solomon", " Ecclesiastes"],
    "answer": " Esther",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Esther"
  },
  {
    "question": "For how many pieces of silver was Joseph sold by his brothers to the Ishmeelites?",
    "choices": [" 10", " 15", " 20", " 25"],
    "answer": " 20",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 37:28"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many apostles did Jesus choose?",
    "choices": [" 10", " 11", " 12", " 13"],
    "answer": " 12",
    "categories": ["new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Luke 6:13"
  },
  {
    "question": "The angel said to Mary that Jesus would 'reign over the house' of which Old Testament character?",
    "choices": [" David", " Abraham", " Jacob", " Moses"],
    "answer": " Jacob",
    "categories": ["old testament", "new testament", "gospels"],
    "reference": "Luke 1:33"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which prophet said, 'Out of Egypt have I called my son'?",
    "choices": [" Isaiah", " Jeremiah", " Hosea", " Ezekiel"],
    "answer": " Hosea",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets"],
    "reference": "Hosea 11:1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of tree did Jesus curse?",
    "choices": [" Olive", " Fig", " Sycamore", " Cedar"],
    "answer": " Fig",
    "categories": ["new testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Mark 11:12-14"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who did Saul request a medium bring up for him?",
    "choices": [" Samuel", " David", " Nathan", " Solomon"],
    "answer": " Samuel",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 28:11"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which Psalm is the verse “He makes me lie down in green pastures, he leads me beside quiet waters,” from?",
    "choices": [" 23", " 51", " 100", " 119"],
    "answer": " 23",
    "categories": ["old testament", "psalms_"],
    "reference": "Psalm 23:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The fear of the Lord is the beginning of...?",
    "choices": [" Knowledge", " Faith", " Wisdom", " Love"],
    "answer": " Wisdom",
    "categories": ["old testament", "proverbs", "psalms"],
    "reference": "Psalm 111:10, Proverbs 9:10"
  },
  {
    "question": "What city did the Lord tell Jonah to preach against?",
    "choices": [" Nineveh", " Sodom", " Gomorrah", " Babylon"],
    "answer": " Nineveh",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets"],
    "reference": "Jonah 1:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these books (Philippians, Colossians, Galatians or Ephesians) come first in the Bible?",
    "choices": [" Philippians", " Colossians", " Galatians", " Ephesians"],
    "answer": " Galatians",
    "categories": ["new testament", "letters_of_paul"],
    "reference": "Contents page"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many chapters does the book Hebrews have?",
    "choices": [" 11", " 12", " 13", " 14"],
    "answer": " 13",
    "categories": ["new testament", "letters_of_paul"],
    "reference": "Hebrews 1-13"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the storm winds which can hit Crete?",
    "choices": [" Euroklydon", " Sirocco", " Bora", " Levant"],
    "answer": " Euroklydon",
    "categories": ["new testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Acts 27:14"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many baskets were left over from the feeding of the 5000?",
    "choices": [" 5", " 7", " 10", " 12"],
    "answer": " 12",
    "categories": ["new testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Matthew 15:3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which disciple found a coin in the mouth of a fish?",
    "choices": [" Peter", " John", " James", " Andrew"],
    "answer": " Peter",
    "categories": ["new testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Matthew 17:24-27"
  },
  {
    "question": "What did Peter find in a fish's mouth?",
    "choices": [" Coin", " Stone", " Bread", " Scroll"],
    "answer": " Coin",
    "categories": ["new testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Matthew 17:24–27"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which book of the bible do we read about Haman?",
    "choices": [" Esther", " Ruth", " Job", " Nehemiah"],
    "answer": " Esther",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Esther 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the only female judge mentioned in the Bible.",
    "choices": [" Deborah", " Ruth", " Esther", " Miriam"],
    "answer": " Deborah",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "Judges 4:4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the wife of King Agrippa, which Paul stood before on trial?",
    "choices": [" Bernice", " Drusilla", " Salome", " Herodias"],
    "answer": " Bernice",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Acts 25:23"
  },
  {
    "question": "How old did Enoch become?",
    "choices": [" 365", " 400", " 500", " 600"],
    "answer": " 365",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 5:23"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the oldest person recorded in the Bible?",
    "choices": [" Noah", " Adam", " Methuselah", " Abraham"],
    "answer": " Methuselah",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 5:27"
  },
  {
    "question": "How old was the oldest person recorded in the Bible?",
    "choices": [" 900", " 950", " 969", " 1000"],
    "answer": " 969",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 5:27"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does Jahwe-Schammah mean?",
    "choices": [
      " God is love",
      " God himself",
      " God with us",
      " God is great"
    ],
    "answer": " God himself",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets"],
    "reference": "Ezekiel 48:35"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many more years did God add to King Hezekiah's life in response to the dying king's prayer?",
    "choices": [" 10", " 12", " 15", " 20"],
    "answer": " 15",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "2 Kings 20:6"
  },
  {
    "question": "What prophetess of the Lord did King Josiah of Judah consult?",
    "choices": [" Huldah", " Miriam", " Deborah", " Anna"],
    "answer": " Huldah",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "2 Kings 22:14-16"
  },
  {
    "question": "What ceremony did King Josiah reinstate that had not been celebrated by any of the previous kings of Israel or Judah?",
    "choices": [
      " Feast of Tabernacles",
      " Passover",
      " Day of Atonement",
      " Feast of Weeks"
    ],
    "answer": " Passover",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "2 Kings 23:21"
  },
  {
    "question": "Upon the return of the ark to Israel, what sacrifice did Samuel offer to the Lord?",
    "choices": [" Ram", " Bull", " Suckling lamb", " Dove"],
    "answer": " Suckling lamb",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 7:9"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name Samuel's firstborn son.",
    "choices": [" Abijah", " Joel", " Eli", " Nathan"],
    "answer": " Joel",
    "categories": ["old testament", "prophets"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 8:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of what tribe of Israel was King Saul?",
    "choices": [" Judah", " Levi", " Benjamin", " Ephraim"],
    "answer": " Benjamin",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 9:21"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the name of king Saul's wife?",
    "choices": [" Michal", " Abigail", " Ahinoam", " Bathsheba"],
    "answer": " Ahinoam",
    "categories": ["old testament", "kings", "judges"],
    "reference": "1 Samuel 14:50"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is required for anyone to understand God's Word?",
    "choices": [" Faith", " Knowledge", " Holy Spirit", " Wisdom"],
    "answer": " Holy Spirit",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "1 Corinthians 2:11"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who did Paul say judged him?",
    "choices": [" Jesus", " The disciples", " The church", " God"],
    "answer": " God",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "1 Corinthians 4:4"
  },
  {
    "question": "___ deferred makes the heart sick?",
    "choices": [" Faith", " Hope", " Love", " Peace"],
    "answer": " Hope",
    "categories": ["old testament", "proverbs"],
    "reference": "Proverbs 13:12"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the Day of Pentecost there came a sound from Heaven of a rushing mighty _____?",
    "choices": [" Fire", " Earthquake", " Wind", " Thunder"],
    "answer": " Wind",
    "categories": ["new testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "Acts 2:2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who offered to pay money for the power to give the Holy Spirit?",
    "choices": [" Simon", " Ananias", " Sapphira", " Cornelius"],
    "answer": " Simon",
    "categories": ["new testament"],
    "reference": "Acts 8 (Simon the Sorcerer)"
  },
  {
    "question": "When Jesus turned water into wine, he converted water that was in stone jars. What were these stone jars normally used for?",
    "choices": [
      " Drinking",
      " Cooking",
      " Ceremonial washing",
      " Storing grain"
    ],
    "answer": " Ceremonial washing",
    "categories": ["new testament", "miracles"],
    "reference": "John 2:6"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many books in the Bible have the name “John” in the title?",
    "choices": [" 2", " 3", " 4", " 5"],
    "answer": " 4",
    "categories": ["new testament", "letter_of_paul"],
    "reference": "John, 1 John, 2 John, 3 John"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which book in the Bible has the shortest title?",
    "choices": [" Job", " Acts", " Jude", " Ruth"],
    "answer": " Job",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Job"
  },
  {
    "question": "What were the names of the three sons of Noah in the order the Bible lists them in?",
    "choices": [
      " Ham, Shem, and Japheth",
      " Japheth, Shem, and Ham",
      " Shem, Ham, and Japheth",
      " Ham, Japheth, and Shem"
    ],
    "answer": " Shem, Ham, and Japheth",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 9:18-19, 1 Chronicles 1:4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was Nimrod’s father?",
    "choices": [" Ham", " Shem", " Cush", " Japheth"],
    "answer": " Cush",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "1 Chronicles 1:10"
  },
  {
    "question": "What were the names of Abraham’s two sons (in order of birth)?",
    "choices": [
      " Isaac and Ishmael",
      " Ishmael and Isaac",
      " Esau and Jacob",
      " Jacob and Esau"
    ],
    "answer": " Ishmael and Isaac",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 16:1-16, 21:1-7, 1 Chronicles 1:28"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Lord changed Abram’s name to Abraham when he was ninety-nine years old, what was his name before that?",
    "choices": [" Abel", " Adam", " Abram", " Ahab"],
    "answer": " Abram",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 17:1-5"
  },
  {
    "question": "How old was Abraham when Isaac was born?",
    "choices": [" 90", " 95", " 100", " 105"],
    "answer": " 100",
    "categories": ["old testament"],
    "reference": "Genesis 21:5"
  }
]
